many years ago long before most of you
were conceived we lived in a Utopia
where if you wanted to use software you
would walk into a store buy a box with a
CD or floppy disc inside of it insert it
into your computer and then it was yours
to keep forever but then one day the
devil got a job as a product manager at
a software company and had this clever
idea called SAS or software as a service
when you buy it you don't actually own
it and just rent it for a monthly fee
until the day you die this caused
profits to go parabolic and nowadays
companies are looking to squeeze the
lemon even harder like pelaton is going
to charge a $95 reactivation fee if you
buy a used bike on Craigslist Logitech
is looking to roll out a pay as youo
Mouse which gives a new meaning to pay
per click an adobe was recently sued by
the FTC for its predatory hidden early
termination fees the only world that
doesn't have this problem is Temple OS
but the reality is that nobody is
forcing you to buy these products in a
free market and the best way to escape
subscription hell is to use free and
open source software Alternatives that
these big companies don't want you to
know about before we get into it make
sure to draw and quarter that like
button and put the subscription button's
head on a pike it really helps out the
channel aside from Windows itself which
can easily be replaced by Linux the most
profitable software of all time is
likely Microsoft Office they get kids
hooked on it in grade school so they can
grow up to spin the hamster wheels that
churn out Microsoft profits luckily
though there's a free and open source
version called Libra office which can do
almost everything that word excel and
PowerPoint do and is compatible with a
crazy number of file formats even
dumpster fires like docx but it is
missing some features from Microsoft
Office like it doesn't require an
internet connection to invade your
privacy it doesn't automatically upload
your documents to the cloud where they
can someday be breached by hackers or
feds and it doesn't have a bunch of AI
garbage built into it if you really want
those features you should continue to
pay Microsoft but if you're looking for
Freedom Libre is the tool now many teams
have escaped Microsoft Office only to
land in other paid tools like air table
which itself is a pretty awesome tool
but extremely expensive at $45 per month
per seat what's crazy though is you
could likely support hundreds of users
on your own VPS for just a few dollars
per month by self-hosting Nob it stores
data in your favorite SQL database but
turns all the tables into Rich
spreadsheets which is ideal for
collaboration but when your boss tells
you to stop collaborate and listen
You'll likely need to use a note-taking
app like notion which is another $10 per
month once again there's an open source
alternative called app flowy which is
written in Rust and flutter not only is
the UI beautiful and can do things like
note taking con bonds and calendars but
noi's most recent Innovation was to shoe
horn AI into the platform well app flowy
can do that too and even let you choose
your own llm provider that's pretty
awesome but you might be wondering how I
find out about all these amazing open
source tools one incredible resource is
daily. deev the sponsor of today's video
it's a website and rapidly growing
community that curates the best
developer content on the internet and
the app itself is a free and open source
project not only will you find the
hottest developer Trends here but you
can also find tune your interest by
joining squads where you'll find other
experienced developers openly discussing
the tech you care about the most and
it's not just a bunch of anonymous Bots
these are real people from the real
world that you can network with to land
a job in real life whether you're
learning to code or just interested in
Tech daily. deev is a website that every
developer should visit on The Daily but
now it's time to talk about another
massive software Juggernaut called
Salesforce they provide customer
relationship management software that
allows salespeople to strategically
annoy you until you buy something
there's a bunch of good open- source
crms but one that stands out is Erp next
which is not only a CRM but also an
enterprise resource planning tool which
can handle accounting quality control
and a bunch of other stuff it's written
in Python and also maintains its own
custom web framework called frappe but
most importantly you can run it in 2
minutes with Docker and cancel your
multi-million dollar Salesforce
contracts now Salesforce also acquired
the popular chat app slack for 27
billion yet another application that you
really don't need to be paying for a
better option is to use a tool like
mattermost which is built with go and
typescript and can be deployed as a
single binary with a postgress database
not only is it packed with features for
chat but also has integrated voice and
video chat it has front-end clients for
the web iOS Android and desktop but most
importantly it gives you total control
over your data a company like slack
can't hold your data hostage and demand
a ransom to get it back but another
thing you might be paying for that
doesn't even need to store data is zoom
back in the pandemic days I once built
my own video conferencing app from
scratch with web RTC and JavaScript but
an even easier approach is to use an
open source tool like jitsy it uses web
RTC under the hood to handle voice
calling but also provides a ton of other
Fe features like mobile applications
raised hands polls virtual backgrounds
and everything else you would expect
from a zoom alternative but if you're
unfortunate enough to be a professional
developer your scrub Master is likely
tortured you with a device called jira
which forces you to do Sprints epics
burnd downs and tickets well the good
news is that there's a tool called plane
that makes this torture device free and
open source it's a torture device for
developers by developers but if you're
developing something you might be using
a tool like Firebase a bass which stands
for big ass backend now I like big back
ends and I cannot lie but I also don't
like paying for them and being locked
into a close- source platform nowadays
there are many great open source
Alternatives like convex aight superbase
pocket base but there's a newcomer you
likely haven't heard of called instant
it's not a full backend but if you're
looking to build a real-time chat or
collaboration tool it handles the client
server sync challenges for you which is
a lot of work to do correctly on your
own but one thing that's relatively easy
to do on your own is host a website yet
many developers choose to pay companies
like forell or Heroku a high premium to
do this for them you can avoid these
taxes with tools like kifi the versel
alternative or daku the Heroku
alternative you can use tools like this
to self-host all of the amazing projects
that we've looked at so far in this
video on a single virtual private server
you get the UI and apis of a premium
hosting platform just without the
massive bills and free toer rug Poes but
now we need to talk about perhaps the
most greedy software developer Adobe I
speak to you as a hypocrite though as I
edit this video in Adobe Premiere for
which I pay a $59 monthly tribute as a
free human being though I could trade
Adobe suite for pirated Adobe suite or
better yet trade premiere for Da Vinci
resolve and trade illustrator for Crea
and trade after effects for blender
virtually every SAS product has a free
and open- Source self-hosted alternative
never paying for software again is going
to be a challenge but remember as
developers we don't do things because
they are easy we do them because we
thought they were going to be easy
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next one